# CLAUDIO LORENZI Bioinformatician, PhD





# **OBJECTIVE**

Committed and enthusiastic bioinformatician with over six years of experience in developing bioinformatics tools and analysing biological data. Confident in working with different programming languages and frameworks. Fast learner and always curious about new technologies, especially in the machine learning field. Collaborative and creative, promoter of a healthy and productive working environment.

# SKILLS

### Data Analysis

RNA-seg, ChIP-seg, Genomics, statistical tests, pathway analysis, basics of protein structure analysis.

#### Machine Learning

Studied at University and used\* during PhD: SVM, Linear and Logistic\* regression, Naive Bayes\*, Decision tree based models\*,

k-NN, Deep Learning,
Perceptron\*, CNN\*, Clustering techniques
(hierarchical\*, k-means\*, EM\*, DBSCAN\*,
SOM\*), feature reduction (PCA\*, NMF,
Autoencoders\*, t-SNE\*), GAN.

Main libraries used: TensorFlow, sk-learn and MLPack.

Additional topics studied on books and online courses:

- Reinforcement Learning and PyTorch (HF certification)
- Transformers and Graph NN (Understanding Deep Learning, S. J.D. Prince, preprint)

## Web/GUI Development

Angular, Node.js (Express.js and Sequelize), mySQL, RESTful API, Electron, Bootstrap,

#### Programming Languages

Python, C++, JavaScript, R, Java (basics)

#### Other tools

Git, Singularity, Docker, Nextflow, VSCode, Eclipse, several bioinformatics tools and

# **LANGUAGES**

Italian English French

Native Proficient Conversational

# **EXPERIENCE**

# Bioinformatician - Postdoc

IOR - Institute of Oncology Research Team: Functional Cancer Genomics

Feb 2022 - Present Bellinzona, CH

Development of a dedicated nexflow pipeline for the preprocessing of the raw data for large cohorts of patients derived prostate cancer RNA-seq samples (PC atlas).

Design, development and implementation of the web application PCaProfiler, currently in beta at pcaprofilertest.tk, that allows the exploration and analysis of the PC atlas.

Analysis of the PC atlas for the identification of cancer specific isoforms. RNA-seq and ChIP-seq data analysis for other projects, including splicing analysis and identification of contaminants.

#### Bioinformatician - PhD candidate

Oct 2018 - Oct 2021 Montpellier, FR

IGH - Institute of Human Genetics

Team: Machine Learning and Gene Regulation

Design, development and implementation of two bioinformatic software: iMOKA and IRFinder-S. Ideated a fast and compacted data structure for large sparse k-mer matrices, used for the identification of relevant features using Machine Learning models.

Implementation of a GUI for iMOKA and Web Application for IRFinder (IRBase) developed with Electron and Angular/Material the first, Express and Angular/Bootstrap the second.

Machine Learning models generated using MLPack (C++), Tensorflow and scikit-learn (Ptython). Software benchmarking and other biology-related statistical analysis (R). Software releases on GitHub, DockerHub and Singularity images.

# Study and Development Engineer

Oct 2016 - Oct 2018 Montpellier, FR

IGH - Institute of Human Genetics

Team: IMGT - the international ImMunoGeneTics information system

Development of bioinformatics pipelines for the manual curation of immunological sequences on an internal Java based web application.

Improvement of the cross-communication of the internal and external databases and integration of information from different origins.

#### **EDUCATION**

PhD in Bioinformatics

University of Montpellier

M.Sc in Bioinformatics

University of Bologna - 110/110 cum laude

B.Sc in Medical Biotechnology University of Milan - 110/110 cum laude

Oct 2018 - Oct 2021 Montpellier, FR

Oct 2014 - Jul 2016 Bologna, IT

Sep 2011 - Sep 2014 Milan, IT

## **PUBLICATIONS**

- iMOKA: k-mer based software to analyze large collections of sequencing data Lorenzi, C., Barriere, S., Villemin, JP. et al. DOI: 10.1186/s13059-020-02165-2
- Genome Biol 22, 307 (2021)
- BMC Biol 19, 70 (2021)
- GECKO is a genetic algorithm to classify and explore high throughput sequencing data Commun Biol 2, 222 (2019)
- Thomas, A., Barriere, S., Broseus, L. et al.
  DOI: 10.1038/s42003-019-0456-9

  NF90 modulates processing of a subset of human pri-miRNAs
  Grasso, G., Higuchi, T., Mac, V., Barbier, J. et al.
  DOI: 10.1093/nar/gkaa386 Nucleic Acids Research 48, 12 (2020)
- ▶ Translesion DNA synthesis-driven mutagenesis in very early embryogenesis of fast cleaving
  - Lo Furno, E., Busseau, I., Aze, A., Lorenzi, C., et al. Nucleic Acids Research 50, 2 (2022) DOI: 10.1093/nar/gkab1223

# PUBLIC PROJECTS

A list of public projects is available here: https://cloxd.github.io/CloXD

# REFERENCES

- ▶ Dr. Theurillat Jean Philippe, Functional Cancer Genomics group Leader, IOR Bellinzona. e-mail: jean-philippe.theurillat@ior.usi.ch phone: +41 58 666 7213
- ▶ Dr. Ritchie William, Machine Learning and Gene Regulation group Leader, IGH Montpellier e-mail: william.ritchie@igh.cnrs.fr or billthebrute@gmail.com phone: +33 7 53 52 92 79